Syed Younus Ali

London, UK

Mobile: 07949972554 Email: syounusa@yahoo.com

Portfolio: Portfolio (syedmyali.github.io) GitHub: https://github.com/syedmyali LinkedIn: syedmyali

NOTE: British Citizen (No work visa or sponsorship required)

Personal Profile

I am an Engineering Professional with several years' experience in the energy and aerospace industry, where I have worked for different companies in engineering, analysis and design role. All of my skills set are in core technical areas and liaise with suppliers, clients and vendors which will be helpful transferable skills in the software development industry.

I'm a fast learner with engineering, design and development mind-set which will be my strengths to excel the potentials in the software development environment.

I'm passionate to be a dedicated software developer through-out my rest of the career.

Technology Skills

Software Development (Front End): HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Typescript, Bootstrap, React, Angular Software Development (Back End): Java, Python, SQL (MySQL, Oracle), NOSQL (Mongo DB) Technology/Frameworks: Maven, Spring Boot, Rest API, Micro services, MVC, JDBC, JUnit, Postman Cloud/ Version Control: AWS (S3, EC2, Elastic Beanstalk, ECS), Azure, Docker, Git, Git Hub, Citrix

HSC Equivalent A Level:

Education and IT Training	
03/2022-06/2022	Infosys Ltd, London
	Enterprise Level Training on Core Java and SQL Database
	Achieved certification after four months professional training
01/2022-03/2022	Just IT Training Ltd, London
	Digital Skills Bootcamp: Software Development
	A twelve week intensive bootcamp covering the fundamentals of full
	stack Software development
10/2021-01/2022	City Lit, London
	Boot Camp: Java Programming
	A twelve week intensive course covering the fundamentals of Java
	programming language
06/2021-09/2021	City Lit, London
	Boot camp: Python Programming
	A four month course covering the python programming language
	and final project
09/2008-10/2009	University of Portsmouth, Portsmouth, UK
	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering
Core Modules:	Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics,
	Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management
Final Year Project:	'Fatigue strength analysis of high chromium alloyed steel specimen'
	supervised by SIEMENS (VAI) and University of Portsmouth.
08/1997-05/2004	Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Bangladesh
	BSc in Mechanical Engineering
Core Modules:	Computer Programming Language, Numerical Analysis, Fluid
	Mechanics, Production Processes, Machine Design, Control
	Engineering, Industrial Management, Renewable Energy
04/1995-04/1997	Dhaka College, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Mathematics (A+), Physics (A+), Chemistry (A+), and English (A)

Projects:

File Management Utility App: The application stores excel files and have view, edit and delete functionalities for each file. It has service access authorization and user authentication capabilities. Programming language and frameworks used: Java, Spring-boot, Angular, MySQL.

University Alumni Tracking Application: The project is a database oriented GUI application which stores the alumni information inputted by individual alumni

Medicine Expiry Checker App: Every year, only in UK alone, tens of millions pounds worth of products are wasted just because of proper expiry checking systems are not in place. This App would be beneficial as it displays the medication expiry time line along with the stock status.

Recently Developed Apps: Weather App (JavaScript), Signup-Login Full Stack App with authentication and authorization (Java, Spring Boot, React), Task Management Micro Services (Java, Spring Boot), Employee Management Full Stack App (Java, Spring Boot, Angular).

Employment History

03/2022-Present

INFOSYS Limited, Canary Wharf London Senior Associate: Software Development

- Currently consulting in B-C and C-B messaging application, Marketflow for the client, Scottish and Southern Electricity Network (SSE PLC).
- Developed full stack applications like **File Management Utility App** for Infosys Accelerate Programme and enterprise clients.

01/2021-05/2021 03/2019-08/2019

Caley Ocean systems Ltd, Glasgow

Senior Mechanical Design Engineer (Contract)

- Carried out Stress/strain/vibration/fatigue and over all structural integrity analysis of mechanical/hydraulic systems in aid of ANSYS, Solid Works, Mathcad and hand calculations.
- Produced 3D prototypes and 2D drawings to relevant standards and best practices.

09/2019-12/2020

Lagoni Engineering, London Senior Design Engineer (Contract)

- Structural analysis of piping, mechanical and hydraulic systems against industry standards, codes and best practices; validated through hand calculations and market leading analysis tools/software.
- Produced, checked and approved engineering documentation (piping material specifications, Pipe supports, data sheet, and manual, SOP, FAT, and Design Review).

10/2017-02/2019

National Oilwell Varco, Glasgow Senior Design Engineer (Contract)

- Generated compliance matrix, data sheet, product specification, Basis of Design (BoD) standard operating procedure (SOP), test plan/procedure.
- Involved in Finite Element Analysis (FEA) and hand calculation to validate the final physical product using industry standard simulation packages.

06/2012-09/2017

Aquaterra Energy Limited, Norwich Mechanical Design Engineer

- Designed prototypes of Topsides, Well Head Support Structure (WSS), Centralisers, Running Tools, Drilling Templates, Tension Ring, Riser Monitoring System (RMS), Lifting System, Test Jigs etc.
- Prepared Factory Acceptance Test report, In house testing, Installation procedure, and Front End Engineering Design report, manufacturing drawings, Bill of Materials, Schematics and Layout.

11/2009-05/2012

GBM Minerals Engineering Limited, London Mechanical Design Engineer

- Participated in client design review for project deliverables and prepared specifications
- Designed mechanical and piping components in AutoCAD Plant 3D.

04/2005-05/2007

Bashundhara Paper Mills Ltd, Bangladesh Assistant Mechanical Engineer